L.P. Allen Collection of Railroad Labor Payrolls 5483
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
L.P. Allen Collection of Railroad Labor Payrolls
1839-1890
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
L. P. Allen
5483
0.83 cubic feet
0.8 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Payroll and financial records of historic Massachusetts and Rhode Island railroads.
5653570
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, July 05, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, July 05, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Old Colony Railroad [OC] was a major railway system that served southeastern Massachusetts and parts of Rhode Island in the 19th century. Initially started to connect Boston with Plymouth, from which it took its name, the OC quickly expanded through a series of mergers with and acquisitions of other established railroads. By 1893, the OC ran over 617 miles of track servicing the Boston metropolitan area, branching out to both industrial and population centers, including Providence, Rhode Island; Newport, Rhode Island; Lowell, Massachusetts; Cape Cod; the South Shore of Massachusetts; New Bedford; Fall River; Fitchburg; and Martha's Vineyard. It even acquired the oldest railroad in the United States, the Granite Railway, in 1870.
In 1893, the OC was purchased by the New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad and was operated as the "Old Colony Division." Many of these lines are still in use today by Amtrak and the Massachusetts Bay Transit Authority.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1839-1890
Bulk dates: 1845-1888
This collection consists of the financial records such as payrolls, stock certificates, cancelled checks, payments received, and paid receipts, from historic railroads in the Massachusetts and Rhode Island areas around Boston and Providence. The records come from the Old Colony Railroad and its predecessor railroads. They were collected by L. P. Allen of Boston, Massachusetts and donated to the Kheel Center in 1975.
These records are an excellent resource for the study of early railroad development in North America. The various financial data found in this collection amply document the types of supplies, and their cost, which were used to construct these early railroads. Invoices include supplies like sperm whale oil, as well as coal and pig iron. The records also show how railroads initially made the majority of their profit off of passenger travel, such as in the 1845 financial reports, in which the revenue from passenger traffic is roughly three time greater than that for freight traffic. The financial statements from the second half of the 19th Century show the reverse, demonstrating the changing nature of the railroading business. The freight and passenger balances from 1888 reflect this change. Additionally, the greater scope of the business is shown by these records as well. The invoices from the early and mid-19th Century are records of business done on a local and regional scale. By 1888, the invoices and accounts paid include businesses from all over the continental United States, illustrating how quickly the railroads were able to span distances and communities that were unimaginable just fifty years previous.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: other railroad collections
Railroads -- Massachusetts -- History.; Railroads -- Rhode Island -- History.; Wages -- Railroads.; Allen, L. P.; Boston and Providence Rail Road and Transportation Company.; Old Colony Railroad.; Boston, Clinton, Fitchburg and New Bedford Railroad; South Shore Railroad; Framingham and Lowell Railroad; Cape Cod Railroad; Providence, Warren and Bristol Railroad; Boston and Lowell Railroad; Boston and Albany Railroad.; Granite Railway.
5653570
- Boston and Providence Railroad Stock Certificates, 1841-1842 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bond Warrants, 1870-1879 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Fitchburg and Worcester Railroad; Boston, Clinton and Fitchburg Railroad.
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Receipts, Paid., 1839 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Stock Sale., 1842 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Stock Sales., 1843 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Receipts, Paid., 1844 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Receipts, Paid., 1845 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Receipts, Labor., 1845 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Receipts, Taxes., 1845 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Roxbury, Massachusetts
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Financial Reports., 1845 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Stock Sales., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Receipts, Labor., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Passenger Receipts, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  For the month of November1855
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Receipts, Paid., 1857 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Receipts, Labor., 1857 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Old Colony and Fall River Railroad. Insurance Policy for Shipment of Rail., 1857 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Stock Sales., 1858 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Receipts, paid., 1858 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Old Colony and Fall River Railroad. Insurance Policies on Shipments of Railroad Iron and Coal., 1858 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, Labor., 1872 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, paid., 1873 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, Paid., 1874 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, Paid., 1875 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, Labor., 1875 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, Taxes, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, Paid, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, Labor., 1876 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, Received., 1876 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Boston, Clinton, Fitchburg and New Bedford Railroad. Cancelled Checks., 1877 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Boston, Clinton, Fitchburg and New Bedford Railroad. Receipts, Paid., 1877 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Boston, Clinton, Fitchburg and New Bedford Railroad. Receipts, Paid., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Boston, Clinton, Fitchburg and New Bedford Railroad. Receipts, Labor., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Boston and Albany Railroad. Cancelled Checks payable to Boston, Clinton, Fitchburg and New Bedford Railroad, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Boston, Clinton, Fitchburg and New Bedford Railroad. Receipts, Labor., 1879 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Boston, Clinton, Fitchburg and New Bedford Railroad. Cancelled Checks., 1879 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, Paid, to Warren Institution for Savings, 1883-1888 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Loan for $50,000 issued February, 1883. Repaid with $1,000 interest August 1888.
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, Paid., 1886 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, Received., 1886 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Old Colony Railroad. Stock Sales., 1886 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, Received., 1887 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Old Colony Railroad. Freight and Passenger Balances., 1888 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Old Colony Railroad. Receipts, Paid, to Merchants Natl. Bank, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  $100,000.00 Loan
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Receipts, Paid. (Box 1, Folder 43)
  Undated
- Post Office's Department. Warrant for Payment. (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Payroll., 1845 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Includes payrolls for Stoughton Branch and Dedham Branch.
- South Shore Railroad. Payroll., 1849 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Providence, Warren and Bristol Railroad. Payroll., 1858 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Payroll., 1858 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Old Colony Railroad. Payroll., 1875 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Old Colony Railroad. Payroll., 1876 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Boston, Clinton, Fitchburg and New Bedford Railroad. Payroll., 1879 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Old Colony Railroad. Payroll., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Boston and Providence Railroad. Receipts, paid., 1845 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Old Colony Railroad, Receipts, paid., 1875 (Box 2, Folder 10)